<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Studio Spring Blog</title>
  <subtitle>UX</subtitle>
  <id>http://studiospring.com.au</id>
  <link href="http://studiospring.com.au"/>
  <link href="http://studiospring.com.au/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sean Loughman</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The what and why of design mentoring</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://studiospring.com.au/2016/mentoring.html"/>
    <id>/2016/mentoring.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-28T00:00:00+11:00</published>
    <updated>2016-11-28T00:00:00+11:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Sean Loughman</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;aside&gt;
  Mentoring is an under-utilised method of professional development whose value, I think, will become more apparent as the design industry matures. Having had some experience on both sides of the fence, as a design tutor at uni, and more recently as a mentee, it is an enriching exchange for both sides and needs to be promoted as such.
&lt;/aside&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;aside&gt;
  Mentoring is an under-utilised method of professional development whose value, I think, will become more apparent as the design industry matures. Having had some experience on both sides of the fence, as a design tutor at uni, and more recently as a mentee, it is an enriching exchange for both sides and needs to be promoted as such.
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is a craft. It is an art and a science. It has theory and practice. Some parts are best learnt in a classroom, other parts can only be learnt through experience. A lot of attention has been paid to the teaching of theory, but practical training has been neglected or co-opted by academia. This is where mentoring comes in and fills the gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pre-industrial times, professional crafts were organised in to guilds, with one function being the accreditation of mastery in that craft. It was only through apprenticeship with a master (or masters) that one could become and be recognised as a master. These days, we share case studies, tips and tricks online and at conferences, but in-depth and personal guidance is often lacking. Mentoring is something few people take part in and is considered by some to be a sign of inexperience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this kind of guidance becomes all the more important as soft skills play a greater role in our work. Soft skills like stakeholder management and design thinking can be developed and perfected endlessly, but are not easily adopted if learnt from a book or even lecture. They need practice and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentoring is somewhat like a long distance apprenticeship. You can touch base with your mentor with specific questions relating to your practice and get an impartial opinion on how you might improve. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging"&gt;Rubber ducking&lt;/a&gt; is another role that your mentor can play. Simply by talking through a problem, the answer can become clearer. Finally, as well as getting a different perspective or approach to a problem, you may find that your mentor agrees with your solution. Receiving that validation that you are doing the right thing is also very empowering and beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although mentoring is a great tool for professional development with unique and compelling advantages, I can't help but think that in some ways it is inferior to a traditional master who watches over your work. Aside from the intermittent contact, which prevents real-time advice, you can't really 'steal from the teacher' by watching how they work. If you are lucky enough to be working with talented peers, then you can engage in some 'stealth' mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest barrier to mentoring is actually finding a suitable mentor (or even any mentor). The supply of mentors rarely keeps up with the demand from mentees. This may partly be because it is difficult to see the benefits of becoming a mentor, while the benefits to a mentee are quite clear. So, let's have a look at the benefits of being a mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only does mentoring broaden your professional network and look good on your resume, it also solidifies your knowledge and deepens your understanding. If you have a good mentee, your own ideas will be challenged and you can see things from a beginner's perspective. It keeps your thinking fresh and breaks down your mental models of design that harden with experience by forcing you to return to the underlying principles of design. Mentoring is also a great chance to practise the fine art of giving feedback and critiquing design. The best mentors give hints so that a mentee can make the journey of discovery for themselves and own the solution rather than provide prescriptive solutions. It also happens to be good fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry is short of senior designers and many designers are the sole designer in an organisation. Mentoring can elevate practical skills across the industry in a way that few other techniques can. Mentoring should be a prerequisite to being recognised as a senior designer, especially when soft skills are so highly valued. We need employers to expect their senior designers to be mentors. There should also be an obligation that mentees become mentors as a way of paying it forward. If we can raise the prestige and value of mentoring, designers and design will be better off for it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A new model for design and innovation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://studiospring.com.au/2016/double-doughnut.html"/>
    <id>/2016/double-doughnut.html</id>
    <published>2016-09-02T00:00:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2016-09-02T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Sean Loughman</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;aside&gt;
  Design has embraced lean and agile workflows and best practice has evolved. Innovation is becoming more important and these practices, adopted from the start up world, are becoming indispensable. Yet models like the double diamond remain unchanged. How can we better describe the process of design and innovation which designers follow today, so that team members and decision makers can understand it and make it a whole-of-organisation process?
&lt;/aside&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;aside&gt;
  Design has embraced lean and agile workflows and best practice has evolved. Innovation is becoming more important and these practices, adopted from the start up world, are becoming indispensable. Yet models like the double diamond remain unchanged. How can we better describe the process of design and innovation which designers follow today, so that team members and decision makers can understand it and make it a whole-of-organisation process?
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a designer, you are probably familiar with the &lt;a href="http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20080821115409/designcouncil.org.uk/en/about-design/managingdesign/the-study-of-the-design-process/"&gt;double diamond&lt;/a&gt; design process model. It was created by the British Design Council in 2005 and is still taught in design schools today. Since then, the process of design has changed, most notably with the adoption of agile practices and a start up mentality. Newer design process models have appeared, but I do not think they illustrate current best practice. Here's my attempt at fixing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1: The British Design Council's double diamond.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/2016/double_diamond.min.svg" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let's set the scene with a little history about design process models. The earliest model that I am aware of is the &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/592952.Universal_Traveler"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Universal Traveler's&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.brainpickings.org/2011/11/11/the-universal-traveler-koberg-bagnall/"&gt;"Traveler's Map"&lt;/a&gt;. This was developed in the 1970s and is remarkably similar to the models that have developed since, suggesting that there is a fundamental approach to creative problem solving. Compared to current thinking, it is a little light on user-centredness, focusing more on the creative process, now known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_thinking#cite_note-21"&gt;design thinking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came the double diamond. What is nice about this model is that it reveals the broadening and narrowing of scope along the design process. The &lt;strong&gt;discovery&lt;/strong&gt; phase is one of casting a broad research net to understand the problem, then distilling that in to a clearly &lt;strong&gt;defined&lt;/strong&gt; problem. &lt;strong&gt;Development&lt;/strong&gt; also expands in scope as you let go of constraints and ideate, only to narrow down and refine the solutions that you ultimately &lt;strong&gt;deliver&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other well known model is the Stanford d.school &lt;a href="http://dschool.stanford.edu/redesigningtheater/the-design-thinking-process/"&gt;design thinking process&lt;/a&gt;. This model is also linear and follows a similar process, but is presented somewhat simplistically. It has since been &lt;a href="https://dschool.stanford.edu/groups/k12/wiki/17cff/Steps_in_a_Design_Thinking_Process.html"&gt;updated&lt;/a&gt; to be more cyclical, at the expense of simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 2: The Stanford d.school design thinking process.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/2016/dschool_process.min.svg" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recently, there have been a number of lean and agile &lt;a href="http://lithespeed.com/lean-ux-dont-part-1-3-2/"&gt;models&lt;/a&gt; which try to show how design fits in. Because agile was developed by programmers, most models are very developer focused and lack a design thinking approach or user focus. The other notable difference is that they are emphatically cyclical unlike previous models. Yet, to my knowledge, there is no authoritative model that designers turn to in order to explain how design can be lean and agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve this problem, I have created a new model and in (a cheeky) homage to the double diamond, named it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Double Doughnut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. It can be divided in to two parts and 6 steps. Though I have broken this process into discrete steps, I prefer to see it as a seamless process with ill-defined boundaries at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 3: The double doughnut.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;img id="double-doughnut" src="/images/2016/double_doughnut.min.svg" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploration&lt;/strong&gt; involves designing a research method and gathering information to understand the problem. Even in later iterations, after a product has been released, there is an exploration to understand problems that arise in the current release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis&lt;/strong&gt; is the process of turning information into knowledge to gain a thorough (but shallow) understanding of the problem-scape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insight&lt;/strong&gt; is the deep understanding of a problem by distilling it into root causes and interrelationships of various parts of the problem-scape. You should be asking the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5_Whys"&gt;5 whys&lt;/a&gt; throughout the entire problem identification stage, but it is particularly important here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ideation&lt;/strong&gt; is the unconstrained generation of the seeds of ideas, to be weeded or cultivated later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Synthesis&lt;/strong&gt; is the convergence of problem, idea and constraints to form a practical solution and reject lesser ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt; is the assessment of a solution's effectiveness by testing with users for the purpose of refining a design. Testing can mean testing a prototype or measuring the effectiveness of a shipped product. Implicit in this step is the understanding that design is never finished and can always be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also worth noting that each circle - problem identification and solution development - can be repeated before progressing to the other circle. So, a couple of research cycles may be needed before the right questions are being asked or the problem is understood well enough to start solving with designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought I could call the double doughnut a design process, but on reflection, it is more than that. It actually is an innovation process. Design is no longer a silo that can be practised within just the design team. Design is no longer just a means of "solving the right problem and solving the problem right". Let's also ask ourselves if we can solve the problem in a fundamentally different and better way by looking at the problem from the ground up. By placing equal importance on the research phase as the design phase (double diamond), exercising design thinking (d.school), iterating in small sprints (agile) and learning from our experiences (lean), it is about innovating (i.e. meeting the needs of the customer in a better way not done before) quickly and competitively. For designers to maximise their potential and innovate, (establishing, rather than just reusing design patterns) the process of innovation needs to be understood and supported by all stakeholders in the organisation. Hopefully, this diagram can help in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to examine the complementary nature of the steps in the two circles to thoroughly understand this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exploration-ideation&lt;/strong&gt;: exploration and ideation are the initial understandings of the problem and solutions respectively. Because you are bootstrapping your understanding of a problem, exploration requires the creativity to imagine scenarios and hypothesise about areas that are worthy of study. Likewise, ideation requires an exploratory mindset in which you probe, question and discover the unimagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis-synthesis&lt;/strong&gt;: both are intermediate steps involving information or ideas that produce patterns or designs which are greater than the sum of their parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insight-testing&lt;/strong&gt;: both are a true understanding of the problem and solution respectively. Only by understanding the root of a problem do you truly understand it. Only by seeing a solution through the eyes of the user do you truly understand its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The double doughnut elegantly illustrates the marriage of traditional design thinking and newer, start up inspired practices. Unsurprisingly, this new best practice encourages user centred innovation. However, it is an end-to-end process that is diminished when even one part is omitted. To execute this process successfully, design thinking must pervade the entire process and users' needs must be given equal weight with business needs and social responsibilities to keep a product competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Understanding heuristics to communicate better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://studiospring.com.au/2016/heuristics-and-communication.html"/>
    <id>/2016/heuristics-and-communication.html</id>
    <published>2016-08-09T00:00:00+10:00</published>
    <updated>2016-08-09T00:00:00+10:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Sean Loughman</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;aside&gt;
  Ever had someone ignore your perfectly rational argument and go against your advice? It could be heuristics! Communication skills are vital to the design profession. Read on and you too can use &lt;em&gt;cognitive bias mitigation&lt;/em&gt; to persuade people better!
&lt;/aside&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;aside&gt;
  Ever had someone ignore your perfectly rational argument and go against your advice? It could be heuristics! Communication skills are vital to the design profession. Read on and you too can use &lt;em&gt;cognitive bias mitigation&lt;/em&gt; to persuade people better!
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soft skills, like collaboration and stakeholder management, are now accepted as vital skills in the design profession. It is also generally understood that we need to tailor our message to different audiences, whether the audience is a different personality or behavioural type, or a different stakeholder within a team. By speaking on the same wavelength, be that emotional or technical, we can convey the intended message and are better able to persuade. I want to show you how to become a better communicator and facilitator by telling you about heuristics and how it influences communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone uses heuristics (also known as rules of thumb or mental short cuts). It saves us time and effort in making judgments. However, it also short circuits our thinking and makes us think in certain ways. I want to examine some pitfalls when using heuristics to communicate design decisions and how to overcome them. In this article I am referring to heuristics relating to general decision-making, not design related heuristics like design patterns or Nielsen's usability heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designers communicate to persuade management, clients or other designers of the value of their work. What they are actually (or should be) communicating are the risks (i.e. the likelihood of success) and rewards of adopting a potential solution. And then the risks and accompanying rewards of all the other possible solutions have to be weighed up to determine the best choice. No wonder heuristics are used!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/2016/risk_reward_matrix.min.svg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as you can see from the diagram, when some rule of thumb offers you a quick solution, heuristics seem to help you select the best choice: low risk, high reward. But they can, according to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heuristic#History"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, lead to suboptimal decisions. I think this is because many heuristics are founded on the premise that past performance is a reliable indicator of future performance (called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Familiarity_heuristic"&gt;familiarity heuristic&lt;/a&gt;). Another one is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Similarity_heuristic"&gt;similarity heuristic&lt;/a&gt;, which people use to select an option that is similar to something that produced a positive experience in the past. More innovative choices are riskier by virtue of their novelty. So, heuristic based decisions can stifle innovation and variety, which leads to solutions that are suboptimal for the business and the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/2016/risk_reward_innovation_matrix.min.svg" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding a third axis of innovation on the next diagram shows how heuristics fall short when measured for innovation, leading to potentially inferior design decisions. When you only choose options based on heuristics your choices suddenly seem quite limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when you, the designer, argue for an optimal solution, decision-makers often lean on heuristics to reach a decision efficiently and minimize perceived risk. The prettiness of a presentation or amount of work perceived to have been put in to it, the latest buzzword or bandwagon are often used to weigh up the argument at hand, instead of judging a proposal purely on its merits. All these signals are useful and important indicators of risk and reward that influence almost everyone to some extent, but they are not always the most reliable indicators and are biased towards established solutions. This is actually an area of study called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_bias_mitigation"&gt;"cognitive bias mitigation"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, heuristics have pros and cons, but if you understand them and the person you are speaking to, you can argue a case more convincingly. First, get on a positive footing by speaking to the heuristic that they use, even if it's not the best or most reliable measure to judge by. Then, reinforce the argument with objective information that can be used to make a rational decision. You also then have a better chance of arguing other points based on that objective information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When heuristics work against you, persuasion is obviously more difficult. One answer is to provide enough information about the choices to make a well thought out decision by doing more research or taking a lean approach and testing and failing fast. Another is to leverage other heuristics that work in your favour, for example, "Company X in industry Y is having great success with Z."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way would be to remind the decision-maker of the consequences of making a wrong decision. Doing this will make them expend more cognitive effort and think through the problem more objectively. When you do this, you will obviously need clear data points to base a decision on for all your choices, because otherwise they will have no choice but to fall back on heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes heuristics such a necessary and fascinating design (and life!) tool, is that everyone uses it is and everyone uses it unconsciously. If you are aiming to produce the best possible outcome and not just 'satisfice', it pays to have a proper understanding of the tools in your tool belt. As a UX designer, I propose solutions and facilitate decision-making, so knowing how to persuade is critical. As a facilitator, the secret to using heuristics appropriately is to know what heuristics are being used by others and leveraging them where possible or discouraging their use and offering a better basis for deciding so that it is easy for others to make decisions wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
